<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2017 Georgia Institute of Technology

Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or
any later version published by the Free Software Foundation.  A copy of
the license is included in gfdl.xml.
*********************************************************************-->

<section xml:id="section-determinant-motivation">
  <title>Determinants: Motivation and First Examples </title>

<p></p>
We begin by recalling three primary goals of this course:
<ol>
	<li> Solving systems of linear equations, a.k.a. solving the matrix equation <m>Ax=b</m> (we've studied this problem in detail).</li>
		<li>Solving the matrix equation <m>Ax=\lambda x</m>, where <m>\lambda</m> is a number (the eigenvalue problem). We are currently studying this problem.</li>
		<li> "Almost solving" the matrix equation <m>Ax=b</m> (we will study this problem).</li>
</ol>
As we have seen that solving matrix equations <m>Ax=b</m> are much easier if we can find an inverse matrix <m>A^{-1}</m>, it is natural to ask for a numerical procedure to quickly test invertibility of matrices. It turns out that there is a very nice answer to this question, which is provided by the theory of <em>determinants</em>. 
<p></p>
Given any <em>square </em> <m>\ n\times n</m> matrix <m>A</m> (there is no such thing as a determinant for a non-square matrix!), the <term>determinant</term> of <m>A</m> is a number, called <m>\det A</m>. We will see several ways to describe this number. 

<p></p>
In fact, determinants are actually an instance of something you already know about: volume. Specifically, the <m>n</m> many columns of a square <m>n\times n</m> matrix <m>A</m> are all <m>n</m>-dimensional vectors. 
These <m>n</m> vectors determine a parallelepiped in <m>\mathbb R^n</m>, which we will call the <em>parallelepiped for <m>A</m>.</em>
For example, if <m>A</m> is a <m>2\times2</m> matrix whose columns are non-zero vectors <m>v</m> and <m>w</m>, that is, if <m>A=\spalignmat{v; w}</m>, then we have the parallelogram determined by <m>v</m> and <m>w</m>:
<figure xml:id="PicPar2Vec">
                    <caption>The parallelgram determined by two vectors <m>v</m> and <m>w</m> in <m>\mathbb R^2</m></caption>
                    <image width="30%" source="images/PicPar2Vec.jpg" />
                </figure>
				<term>NOTE: Images aren't loading properly for some reason, although I believe they're in the right folder.</term>
				Similarly, if <m>A</m> is a <m>3\times3</m> matrix, then we obtain three vectors in <m>\mathbb R^3</m>, which define a parallelepiped:
				<figure xml:id="PicPar3Vec">
				                    <caption>The parallelepiped determined by three vectors in 
									<m>\mathbb R^3</m></caption>
				                    <image width="30%" source="images/PicPar3Vec.jpg"/>
				                </figure>
								
<p></p>
<term>Key Obversvation:</term> 
The matrix <m>A</m> is invertible if and only if the parallelepiped for <m>A</m> has non-zero volume, i.e., if and only if the parallelepiped is not "flat". 

<p></p>
This is not too hard to believe, especially in low-dimensional cases. 
For example, if <m>A</m> is a <m>2\times2</m> matrix whose columns are non-zero vectors <m>v</m> and <m>w</m>, then we know that the matrix is invertible exactly when <m>v</m> and <m>w</m> are linearly independent, which happens exactly when they don't lie on the same line (neither is a scalar multiple of the other). But this occurs exactly when the parallelogram for <m>A</m> in <xref ref="PicPar2Vec"/> isn't "squashed."
<p></p>
We shall later see that the determinant of <m>A</m> is a number associated to <m>A</m> 
whose absolute value <em>is</em> the volume of the parallelepiped for <m>A</m>.

<p></p>
Before jumping into general formulas for and the definition of the determinant, we consider a few examples. If <m>n=1</m>, then 
we know that a real number <m>a</m> is invertible (i.e., <m>1/a</m> makes sense) exactly when <m>a\neq0</m>. It is thus reasonable to define the determinant of the matrix <m>\spalignmat{a}</m> to simply be <m>a</m> itself. That is, for any real number <m>a</m>, we have
 $$\det\spalignmat{a}=a.$$
 In this case, we can also think of <m>1</m>-dimensional "volume" as length, and the "parallelepiped for <m>A</m>" is just the vector <m>a</m> in <m>\mathbb R^1</m>.
 <p></p>
		In the case of a <m>2\times2</m> matrix <m> A=\spalignmat{a,b; c,d}</m>, the explicit formula is 
		$$
		\det A
		=ad-bc.
		$$ 
		It may seem that this formula has little to do with volume. However, it is a fun geometry problem to show that the parallelogram for <m>A</m> in <xref ref="PicPar2Vec"/> has area <m>|ad-bc|</m> (first think about the case when the first column of <m>A</m> lies on the <m>x</m>-axis). As another fun problem, one can perform row reduction directly on <m>A</m> to find that the reduced row echelon form of <m>A</m> is the identity matrix <m>I_2</m> exactly when <m>ad-bc\neq0</m> (although we omit the calculation here).
		<p></p>
		When <m>n=3</m>, the formula for the determinant is a little stranger:
		$$
		\begin{split}
		&amp;
		\det\spalignmat{a_{11},a_{12},a_{13}; a_{21},a_{22},a_{23},a_{31},a_{32},a_{33}}
		\\
		&amp;
		\quad\quad
		=
		a_{11}a_{22}a_{33}+a_{12}a_{23}a_{31}+a_{13}a_{21}a_{32}
		-a_{13}a_{22}a_{31}-a_{11}a_{23}a_{32}-a_{12}a_{21}a_{33}
		.
		\end{split}
		$$
		This formula looks too complicated to memorize outright. Fortunately, there is a useful mnemonic device for this formula, known as the <em>Rule of Sarrus</em>. This works by drawing a bigger matrix by recopying down the first two columns to the right of the matrix, and by drawing a series of upwards and downwards slashes as follows:
		<term>NOTE: Figure out how to color text (usual html command doesn't work) and how to draw the matrices with slashes.</term>
		Then, we multiply all the entries on each slash together, and add the products of the downward ones, and subtract the products of the upwards ones. For example, 
		<term> NOTE: Insert example with numbers once I figure out how to draw the picture with slashes above.</term>
		
		<p></p>
		Beyond <m>n=3</m>, the formula for the determinant gets more complicated. In the subsequent sections, we will give several different ways for computing the determinant, we will apply them to give a general formula for the inverse of a matrix, and we will see how they can be thought of as stretch factors for linear transformations. That’s a lot to do, so let’s get going!
		
  

</section>