<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2017 Georgia Institute of Technology

Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or
any later version published by the Free Software Foundation.  A copy of
the license is included in gfdl.xml.
*********************************************************************-->

<exercises>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				<ol>
					<li>Give a set that is closed under scalar multiplication but not addition.</li>
					<li>Give a set closed under addition but not scalar multiplication.</li>
					<li>Give a set closed under neither.</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</statement>
		<answer>
			<p>
				<ol>
					<li>The union of the <m>x</m>-axis and the <m>y</m>-axis in <m>\R^2</m> is one.</li>
					<li>The set of integers, as a subset of <m>\R^1</m>, is one.</li>
					<li>The subset <m>\left\{\vec{v}\right\}</m> of <m>\R^2</m> is one, where <m>\vec{v}</m> is any nonzero vector.</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</answer>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>True or false.
				<ol>
					<li>The solution set to any consistent system of linear equations is a subspace.</li>
					<li>The solution set to a consistent system of linear equations of the form <m>Ax=0</m> is a subspace.</li>
					<li>The set of points where two subspaces meet (i.e., the collection of points that are in both subspaces) is a subspace. For example, consider the set of points that lie on the intersection of two planes, or on a plane and a line.</li>
					<li>Given any two subspaces <m>V</m> and <m>W</m>, the collection of points that are in one or both of <m>V</m> or <m>W</m> is a subspace. For example, the collection of points on either or both of the lines <m>y=x</m> and <m>y=-x</m> is the cross-shaped <q>X</q>, and includes their intersection point at the origin.</li>
					<li>If <m>A</m> is a square matrix and the equation <m>Ax=0</m> has only the trivial solution <m>x=0</m>, then the equation <m>Ax=b</m> has a solution for every appropriately-sized vector <m>b</m> . </li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</statement>
		<answer>
			<p>
				<ol>
					<li>False. For example, the solution set of the set of equations <m>x+y=3</m> in <m>\R^2</m> is a line, but doesn't pass through the origin.</li>
					<li>True. Here, we can check the axioms in the definition of a subspace. Given the shape of the equation <m>Ax=0</m>, we clearly have that the zero vector solves this equation, and so the solution set contains the origin (which solves the problem encountered in the last example). Now, suppose that <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are solutions. Then <m>A(x+y)=Ax+Ay=0+0=0</m>, and so <m>x+y</m> also solves the system, and  for a real number <m>\alpha</m>, <m>A(\alpha x)=\alpha Ax=\alpha0=0</m>, and
					so <m>\alpha x</m> is a solution too. Thus, the solution set satisfies parts 2 and 3 of the definition of a subspace, and hence is a subspace. </li>
					<li>True. Suppose that <m>V</m> and <m>W</m> are both subspaces of <m>\R^n</m>.
					 Then we can check each part of the definition is satisfied by the set of points where <m>V</m> and <m>W</m> meet. 
					 Firstly, since <m>0</m> is in both subspaces, its in this new set, so it is a nonempty set. 
					 Furthermore, if <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are in the set and <m>\alpha</m> is a real number, then <m>\alpha x+y</m> is in the set, 
					 using the axioms in the definition of subspace applied twice, once using the fact that <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are in particular both in <m>V</m>
					 , and once using that they are both in <m>W</m>. Note that this implies both the second and third parts of the definition of subspace, as we can take <m>\alpha=1</m> for part 2 of the definition, and choose <m>y=0</m> for part 3 of the definition. </li>
					 <li>False. Although this always contains the origin, it will usually not be a subspace. 
					 For instance, consider the two lines <m>y=\pm x</m> in <m>\R^2</m>. The collection of points in one or both of these lines is not closed under addition. 
					 To see this, we just need a counter example. For instance, choose <m>(1, -1)</m> on the line <m>y=-x</m> and the point <m>(2, 2)</m> on the line <m>y=x</m>. 
					 In particular, both of these points are on the <q>X</q> figure. 
					 However, the sum of these two points, <m>(1,-1)+(2,2)=(3,-1)</m>, is not on either of the two lines, as <m>3\neq\pm(-1)</m>. </li>
					<li>True. By the Rank Theorem, the equation <m>Ax=0</m> (which is consistent, as it automatically has the solution <m>x=0</m> gives rise to an equation (dimension of column span) <m>+</m> (dimension of solution set)<m>=</m> number of variables, say <m>n</m>.
					The question postulates that the dimension of the solution set is <m>0</m> (it is just the point at the origin), and so the dimension of the column span is <m>n</m>. Thus, every vector in <m>\R^n</m> is a linear combination of the columns of 
					<m>A</m>, i.e., the equation <m>Ax=b</m> has a solution for every <m>n</m>-dimensional vector <m>b</m>. </li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</answer>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>Suppose that <m>A</m> is the matrix
				<me>
					A = \mat{
					2 1;
					6 5;
					2 4
					}
				</me>
				<ol>
					<li>Explain in words how knowing all solutions to <em><m>Ax=b</m></em> decides if a given vector <em><m>b</m></em> is in the column space of A.</li>
					<li>Is the vector <m>b=\vec{8 28 14}</m> in the column space of A?</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</statement>
		<answer>
			<p>
				<ol>
					<li>The column space of <m>A</m> contains all linear combinations of the columns of <m>A</m>, which are precisely the vectors of the form <m>Ax</m> for an arbitrary vector <m>x</m>. Thus <m>Ax=b</m> has a solution if and only if <m>b</m> is in the column space of <m>A</m>.</li>
					<li>Yes. Reducing the matrix combining <m>A</m> and <m>b</m> gives
						<me>
							\amat{
							2 1 8;
							6 5 28;
							2 4 14
							}
							\quad\xrightarrow{}\quad
							\amat{
							2 1 8;
							0 2 4;
							0 3 6
							}
							\quad\xrightarrow{}\quad
							\amat{
							2 1 8;
							0 2 4;
							0 0 0
							}
						</me>
						Thus, <m>x=\vec{3 2}</m> is a solution to <m>Ax=b</m>, and b is in the column space of <m>A</m>.
					</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</answer>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>Suppose <m>A</m> is the matrix
				<me>
					A=\mat{
					0 1 2 2;
					0 3 8 7;
					0 0 4 2
					}
				</me>
				<ol>
					<li>Find all special solutions to <m>Ax=0</m> and describe in words the whole nullspace of <m>A</m>.</li>
					<li>Describe the column space of <m>A</m>. <q>All combinations of four columns</q> is not a sufficient answer.</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</statement>
		<answer>
			<p>
				<ol>
					<li>First, by row reduction
						<md>
							<mrow>
								\mat{
								0 1 2 2;
								0 3 8 7;
								0 0 4 2
								}
								\quad\xrightarrow{}\quad
								\mat{
								0 1 2 2;
								0 0 2 1;
								0 0 4 2
								}
								\quad\xrightarrow{}\quad
								\mat{
								0 1 0 1;
								0 0 2 1;
								0 0 0 0
								}
							</mrow>
							<mrow>
								\quad\xrightarrow{}\quad
								\mat{
								0 1 0 1;
								0 0 1 \frac{1}{2};
								0 0 0 0
								}
							</mrow>
							
						</md>
						so the special solutions are <m>s_1=\vec{1 0 0 0}, s_2=\vec{0 -1 -\frac{1}{2} 1}</m>. Thus <m>\Nul(A)</m> is a plane in <m>\R^4</m> given by all linear combinations of the special solutions.
					</li>
					<li>
						<m>\Col(A)</m> is a plane in <m>\R^3</m> given by all combinations of the pivot columns, namely
						<me>
							c_1 \cdot \vec{1 3 0} + c_2 \cdot \vec{2 8 4}
						</me>
					</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</answer>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>Let <m>A</m> be a <m>2 \times 2</m> matrix such that <m>\Nul(A)</m> is the line <m>y=x</m>. Let <m>b</m> be a <em>nonzero</em> vector in <m>\R^2</m>. Which of the following are definitely not the solution set of <m>Ax = b</m>?
				<ol>
					<li>The line <m>y=x</m>.</li>
					<li>The <m>y</m>-axis.</li>
					<li>The line <m>y=x+1</m>.</li>
					<li>The set <m>\left\{0\right\}</m>.</li>
					<li>The empty set.</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</statement>
		<answer>
			<p>1, 2, and 4. The solution set of <m>Ax = b</m> is either empty or a translate of <m>\Nul(A)</m> by a nonzero vector, namely, a specific solution to <m>Ax = b</m>.</p>
		</answer>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>If <m>A</m> is a <m>3 \times 3</m> matrix, is it possible that <m>\Col(A) = \Nul(A)</m>?</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>[MIT OCW] If <m>\Col(B)</m> is a subspace of <m>\Nul(A)</m>, then either (choose one) <m>AB</m> or <m>BA</m> must be simply <fillin/>.
			</p>
		</statement>
		<answer>
			<p><m>AB=0</m>. The reason is that for any vector <m>x</m>, <m>Bx \in \Col(B) \subseteq \Nul(A)</m>, so <m>ABx=0</m>. But the only way <m>ABx=0</m> for all <m>x</m> can be true is if <m>AB=0</m>.</p>
		</answer>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>[MIT OCW] Suppose <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> are <m>3 \times 3</m> matrices.
				<ol>
					<li>If a vector <m>v</m> is in the column space of <m>AB</m>, why is <m>v</m> also in the column space of <m>A</m>?</li>
					<li>Give an example of <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> so that <m>\Col(AB)</m> is smaller than <m>\Col(A)</m>.</li>
					<li>If a vector <m>v</m> is in the column space of <m>AB</m>, this does not necessarily mean it is in the column space of <m>B</m>. Give an example of <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> and a vector <m>v</m> that is in <m>\Col(AB)</m> but not <m>\Col(B)</m>.</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</statement>
		<answer>
			<p>
				<ol>
					<li><m>v</m> being in the column space of <m>AB</m> means that there is an <m>x</m> such that <m>ABx=v</m>. But then if we take <m>y=Bx</m>, then <m>Ay=ABx=v</m>, so <m>v</m> is in the column space of <m>A</m>.</li>
					<li>If we take <m>A=\mat{1 0 0;0 0 0;0 0 0}</m> and <m>B=\mat{0 0 0;0 0 0;0 0 1}</m>, then <m>AB=0</m>, so its column space is <m>Z</m>(only the zero is the vector), but the column space of <m>A</m>
					 is the line through <m>\vec{1 0 0}</m>.</li>
					 <li>We can take <m>A</m> to be the <m>3 \times 3</m> matrix that permutes the first two coordinates, so
					 	<me>A=\mat{0 1 0;1 0 0;0 0 1}</me>
					 	Then if <m>C(B)</m> is a line generated by <m>\vec{1 0 0}</m>, then <m>\Col(AB)</m> is generated by <m>\vec{0 1 0}</m>. So we can take
					 	<me>A=\mat{0 1 0;1 0 0;0 0 1}, B=\mat{1 1 1; 0 0 0;0 0 0}, and v=\vec{0 1 0}</me>.
					 </li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</answer>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>[MIT OCW] Suppose the matrices <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> have the same column space. Give
an example where <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> have different nullspaces - or reason why this is impossible.</p>
		</statement>
		<answer>
			<p>The simplest way to provide an example is to add dependent columns to matrix <m>A</m>. For example, matrices <m>\mat{1}</m> and <m>\mat{1 0}</m> have the same column space and different null spaces.</p>
		</answer>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>[MIT OCW] If <m>B</m> is a square matrix then <m>\Col(B) = \Col(B^T)</m>. True or False.</p>
		</statement>
		<answer>
			<p>False. Consider <m>B=\mat{0 1; 0 0}</m>. Then the column space of <m>B</m> is <m>\vec{1 0}</m> and the column space of <m>B^T</m> is <m>\vec{0 1}</m>.</p>
		</answer>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>[MIT OCW]
				<ol>
					<li>Suppose you are given nonzero column vectors <m>r,n,c,l \in \R^2</m>. Explain how to determine if these vectors can form bases for the 4 fundamental subspaces,
row space, nullspace, column space and left nullspace respectively, and output a matrix with those 4 fundamental subspaces if possible. <em>Hint</em>: Think about orthogonality of the four subspaces. Express matrix in terms of the vectors above.</li>
					<li>Suppose you are given 4 matrices whose columns are all vectors in <m>\R^{10}</m>. <m>R=\mat{r_1 r_2 \ldots, r_i}, N = \mat{n_1 n_2 \ldots, n_j}, C=\mat{c_1 c_2 \ldots, c_i}</m>, <m> L=\mat{l_1 l_2 \ldots, l_n}</m>.
						The columns of <m>R</m> form a basis for the row space, the columns of <m>N</m> form a basis for the nullspace, the columns of <m>C</m> form a basis for the column space, and the columns of
						<m>L</m> form a basis for the left nullspace. Explain how to determine if these vectors form the basis for the four fundamental subspaces, ad output a
matrix that has those four subspaces.
					</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</statement>
		<answer>
			<p>
				<ol>
					<li>By the orthogonality of the fundamental subspaces, we must have <m>r \cdot n = r^T \cdot n =0</m>, <m>c \cdot l = c^T \cdot l = 0</m>. If the 4 column vectors satisfies the above condition,
					 <m>A=cr^T</m> is a matrix satisfies the condition.</li>
					<li>Use the same idea above. By the orthogonality of the fundamental subspaces, we must have <m>R^T N=0, C^T L=0</m>. e also need the dimension to match, i.e.
					 <m>i+j = i+n = 10</m>. Under the condition above, <m>A=CR^T</m> is a matrix satisfies the condition.</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</answer>
	</exercise>
</exercises>
