<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2017 Georgia Institute of Technology

Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or
any later version published by the Free Software Foundation.  A copy of
the license is included in gfdl.xml.
*********************************************************************-->
<exercises>
    <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>A</m> be a symmetric matrix. Explain step by step how to find an orthonormal basis of eigenvectors of <m>A</m>. (Be sure to consider the case when not all eigenvalues of <m>A</m> are distinct).</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>
    <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>A</m> be a symmetric matrix. Explain step by step how to find an matrix <m>U</m> and a diagonal matrix <m>D</m> such that <m>A = UDU^T</m> and <m>U^T = U\inv</m>.</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>
    <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>A</m> be a symmetric matrix. Explain step by step how to find a spectral decomposition of <m>A</m>.</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>
    <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>A</m> be a symmetric matrix. If <m>\lambda</m> is a root of <m>\det(A-\lambda I)</m> of multiplicity <m>k</m> , explain why the null space of <m>A-\lambda I</m> has dimension <m>k</m>.</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>
    <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>A</m> be a symmetric matrix with eigenvalues <m>\lambda_1, \lambda_2</m> and the corresponding eigenvectors <m>v1, v2</m>. Assume <m>\lambda_1 = \lambda_2</m>. Explain why <m>v1, v2</m> are orthogonal.</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>
    <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>Q: \R^n\to\R</m> be a quadratic form, that is, a function of the form <m>\sum_{i, j=1}^n a_{ij} x_i x_j</m> where <m>a_{ij}</m> are real numbers and <m>x_k</m> is the <m>k</m>th coordinate on <m>\R^n</m>. Explain how to find a symmetric <m>n \times n</m> matrix <m>A</m> such that <m>Q(x)=Ax\cdot x</m> for all <m>x</m> in <m>\R^n</m>.</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>
    <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>Q(x) = Ax\cdot x</m> where <m>A</m> is a symmetric <m>n \times n</m> matrix with eigenvalues <m>\lambda_1, \ldots , \lambda_n</m>. Explain how to find a change of variables so that <m>Q</m> becomes <m>\lambda_1 {y_1}^2 + \cdots + \lambda_n {y_n}^2</m>).</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>
    <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>Q(x) = Ax\cdot x</m> where <m>A</m> is a symmetric <m>n \times n</m> matrix. Explain why <q><m>Q(x) > 0</m> for every <m>x \neq 0</m> if and only if every eigenvalue of <m>A</m> is positive</q>.</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>
    <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>Q(x) = Ax\cdot x</m> where <m>A</m> is a symmetric <m>n \times n</m> matrix. Explain why <q><m>Q(x) \geq 0</m> for every <m>x \neq 0</m> if and only if every eigenvalue of <m>A</m> is nonnegative</q>.</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>
    <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>Q(x) = Ax\cdot x</m> where <m>A</m> is a symmetric <m>n \times n</m> matrix with eigenvalues <m>\lambda_1, \ldots , \lambda_n</m> and an orthonormal basis of eigenvectors <m>u_1,\ldots, u_n</m>, where <m>Au_i=\lambda_i u_i</m>. What are the maximum and the minimum of the function <m>Q(x)</m>Q(x) under the constrain <m>\|x\|=1</m>? For which <m>x</m> are the the maximum and the minimum attained?</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>
    <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>Let <m>A</m> be a symmetric <m>n \times n</m> such that <m>Q_A(x) = Ax\cdot x</m> is positive definite. Explain why the matrix <m>A\inv</m> is invertible and symmetric. Explain why the quadratic form <m>Q_{A\inv}(x) = A\inv x\cdot x</m> is positive definite.</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>
    <exercise>
        <statement>
            <p>If <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> are symmetric matrices whose eigenvalues are positive, explain why the eigenvalues of <m>A+B</m> are positive.</p>
        </statement>
    </exercise>
    <exercise>
    	<statement>
    		<p>[MIT OCW] Suppose <m>u</m> is a unit vector in <m>\R^n</m>, so <m>u^T u=1</m>. This problem is about <m>n \times n</m> symmetric matrix <m>H = I - 2uu^T</m>.
    			<ol>
    				<li>Show directly that <m>H^2 = I</m>. Since <m>H=H^T</m>, we now know that <m>H</m> is not only symmetric but also <fillin/>.</li>
    				<li>One eigenvector for <m>H</m> is <m>u</m> itself. Find the corresponding eigenvalue.</li>
    				<li>If <m>v</m> is any vector perpendicular to <m>u</m>, show that <m>v</m> is an eigenvector of <m>H</m> and find the eigenvalue. With all these eigenvectors <m>v</m>, that eigenvalue must be repeated how many times? Is <m>H</m> diagonalizable? Why or Why not?</li>
    				<li>Find the diagonal entries <m>H_{11}</m> and <m>H_{ii}</m> in terms of <m>u_1 \ldots u_n</m>. Add up <m>H_{11} + \ldots + H_{nn}</m> and separately add up the eigenvalues of <m>H</m>.</li>
    			</ol>
    		</p>
    	</statement>
    	<answer>
    		<p>
    			<ol>
    				<li>Explicitly, we find <m>H^2=(I-2uu^T)^2=I^2-4uu^T +4uu^T uu^T</m> since <m>uu^T = 1, H^2=I</m>. Since <m>H=H^T</m>, we also have <m>H^T H=1</m>, implying that <m>H</m> is also an orthogonal matrix.</li>
    				<li>Since <m>Hu=(I-2uu^T)u = u-2uu^T u= u-2u = -u</m>, <m>\lambda=1</m>.</li>
    				<li>For any vector <m>v</m> orthogonal to <m>u</m>, we have <m>Hv=(I-2uu^T)v=v-2uu^T v=v</m>, so the associated <m>\lambda=1</m>. The orthogonal complement to the space spanned by <m>u</m> has dimension <m>n-1</m>, so there is a basis of <m>(n-1)</m> orthonormal eigenvectors with this eigenvalue. Adding in the eigenvector <m>u</m>, we find that <m>H</m> is diagonalizable.</li>
    				<li>Since the <m>i</m>th diagonal entry of <m>uu^T </m> is <m>u_i^2</m>, the <m>i</m> diagonal entry of <m>H</m> is <m>H_{ii}=1-2u_i^2</m>. Summing these together gives <m>\sum_{i=1}^n H_{ii}=n-2\sum_{i=1}^n u_i^2=n-2</m>. Adding up the eigenvalues of <m>H</m>
    				also gives <m>\sum \lambda_i=(1)-1+(n-1)(1)=n-2</m>.</li>
    			</ol>
    		</p>
    	</answer>
    </exercise>
    <exercise>
    	<statement>
    		<p>[MIT OCW] Suppose <m>A</m> is a positive definite symmetric <m>n \times n</m> matrix.
    			<ol>
    				<li>How do you know that <m>A\inv</m> is also positive definite?</li>
    				<li>Suppose <m>Q</m> is any orthogonal <m>n \times n</m> matrix. How do you know that <m>QAQ^T = QAQ\inv</m> is positive definite? Which test would you use?</li>
    				<li>Show that the block matrix 
    					<me>B = \mat{A A; A A}</me>
    					is positive semidefinite. How do you know that <m>B</m> is not positive definite?
    				</li>
    			</ol>
    		</p>
    	</statement>
    	<answer>
    		<p>
    			<ol>
    				<li>Since a matrix is positive-definite if and only if all its eigenvalues are positive, and since the eigenvalues of <m>A\inv</m> are simply the inverses of the eigenvalues of <m>A</m>, <m>A\inv</m> is also positive definite (inverse of a positive number is positive).</li>
    				<li>Using the energy test (x^T Ax > 0 for nonzero x), we find that <m>x^T QAQ^T x = (Q^T x)^T A(Q^T x) > 0</m> for all nonzero <m>x</m> as well (since <m>Q</m> is invertible). Using the positive
    				eigenvalue test, since <m>A</m> is similar to <m>QAQ\inv</m> and similar matrices have the same eigenvalues, <m>QAQ\inv</m> also has all positive eigenvalues.</li>
    			</ol>
    		</p>
    	</answer>
    </exercise>
    <exercise>
    	<statement>
    		<p>If <m>A</m> is any <m>m \times n</m> matrix with <m>m \gt n</m>, tell me why <m>AA^T</m> cannot be positive definite. Is <m>A^T A</m> always positive definite? (If not, what is the test on <m>A</m>?)</p>
    	</statement>
    	<answer>
    		<p><m>AA^T</m> is an <m>m \times m</m> matrix but its rank is not greater than <m>n</m> (all columns of <m>AA^T</m> are combinations of columns of <m>A</m>). Since <m>n \lt m</m>, <m>AA^T</m> is singular. 
    		<m>A^T A</m> is positive definite if <m>A</m> has full column rank <m>n</m> (Not always true, <m>A</m> can even be a zero matrix).</p>
    	</answer>
    </exercise>
</exercises>
